[The Age of Awakening]
[觉醒年代]
[Episode Thirty-five]
[第三十五集]
Shouchang, I have made up my mind.
守常 我是下了决心了
Let's meet at Dagoutou tomorrow noon.
明日中午我们大沟头碰面
One of us will go there
咱俩一人一半
half the night.
晚上去撒
You know what?
这样吧
[Chen Duxiu, styled Zhongfu, Professor at Peking University]
[陈独秀 字 仲甫 北京大学教授]
We'll talk about this tomorrow when we meet.
这事明天咱俩见面时候再说
Give me the manuscript first.
你先把稿子给我
About handing out flyers tomorrow,
明天撒传单的事儿
don't let Yannian know.
别让延年知道
Don't involve Yannian, either.
也别奉扯上延年
I don't want him involved.
我不想让他掺和进来
Come on.
走吧
[Li Dazhao, styled Shouchang, Director of Peking University Library]
[李大钊 字 守常 北京大学图书馆主任]
Why did you come back alone?
你怎么一个人回来了
Uncle Hu threw up. Auntie is helping to clean up.
胡叔叔吐了 姨妈帮看收拾呢
I asked you why you came back alone.
我问你怎么一个人回来了
Who told you to come back?
谁让你回来的
I came back by myself
我自己回来的
Let me ask you something.
我问您件事
Will you hand out leaflets tomorrow?
明天发传单您去不去
I won't go.
我不去
Shouchang has already arranged it.
守常都已经安排了
Okay. I'll print the flyers.
行 那印传单我去
No need.
不用
I've already arranged everything.
我都已经安排了
This declaration and wax paper
这份宣言和蜡纸
were collected from the mimeograph society
是我们从大沟头
at 18 Dagoutou.
十八号的油印社搜缴来的
We analyzed that
我们分析
it's very likely that this declaration was circulated internally
这份宣言极有可能是内部传看
or just posted downtown.
或者只在闹市区张贴
Judging from the writing and handwriting of this declaration,
从这份宣言的文笔和字迹看
[Wu Bingxiang, Chief of the Metropolitan Police Department]
[吴炳湘 京师警察厅总监]
Chen Duxiu should have done it.
应该是陈独秀所为
So it's likely that
所以他很有可能
he will personally handle this declaration.
会亲自处理这份宣言
It is recommended to immediately increase the number
建议 立即在各闹市区
of plainclothes police officers in downtown areas
增加便衣警力
to catch the perpetrators on the spot.
争取现场抓获肇事者
You mean that
你的意思是说
Chen Duxiu and Li Dazhao
陈独秀和李大钊
will hand out leaflets in person?
会亲自上街散发传单
With my research on Chen Duxiu,
以我对陈独秀的研究
it's not completely impossible.
并非完全没有可能
Even if it's not Chen Duxiu,
即便抓到的不是陈独秀
we can also follow the trail.
我们也可以顺藤摸瓜
We just confirmed
只要确认
that this "Beijing Citizen Manifesto"
这份《北京市民宣言》
was drafted by Chen Duxiu.
是陈独秀起草的
You can arrest him as well.
一样可以逮捕他
I'll give you credit for catching Chen Duxiu.
抓住陈独秀我记你一功
Yes.
是
Stop pretending, madam.
别装了 师母
I can't eat so much alone.
我一个人也吃不了这么多
Madam doesn't have any good gifts for you either.
师母也没什么好礼物送给你
I know you like to eat my baozi.
知道你喜欢吃我包的包子
I'll bring you more food for the road.
给你多带点 路上吃
I'm here to say goodbye to you and your husband,
我这来跟您跟先生辞行的
and I still have the result.
结果还拿着走
It's okay.
没事
Come and pack it.
来 装好
Yannian. Qiaonian.
延年乔年
You two are not going to see me off?
你俩不打算送送我
We are.
送 送啊
Yeah.
送
We're going to.
送送送
We'll all see you off.
我们都送你
Qunxian.
群先
Hello, sir.
先生好
I came to say goodbye to you.
我是过来跟您辞行的
I know.
知道
I'll give you a present when you leave.
临行我也送给你一件礼物
I wrote an inscription.
写了一幅字
The young girl Jingwei
女娃为精卫
fills the Eastern Sea with pebbles,
衔石堙东海
the Eastern Sea remains unfilled
东海水未堙
yet the girl's heart remains unchanged.
女娃心已改
Kuafu runs to Yuyuan (=legendary place with no sun)
夸父走虞渊
chasing the sun,
白日终相待
with a heart of stone,
奈何金石心
he sits idly by and regrets.
坐视生吝悔
This poem was written in 1910,
这首诗是一九一○年
I wrote it when I was in the deepest depression in Hangzhou,
我在杭州精神最苦闷时写下的
it was one of twenty poems.
二十首诗中的其中一首
It mainly expresses
主要是想表达
that if you want to be a revolutionary,
要想成为革命者
you must be not afraid of failure
就要不怕失败
and have an indomitable spirit.
要有不屈不挠的精神
It is a kind of hope
今日送给你们这些青年人
to give you young people today.
就算是一种希望吧
Thanks again, sir.
再次谢谢先生
Let's go, don't miss the train.
走吧 别误了火车
Okay.
好
Let's go. I'll walk you out.
走 我送你出去
Goodbye, sir.
先生再见
Goodbye, sister Qunxian.
群先姐姐再见
Goodbye, Henian, Zimei.
再见 鹤年子美
Henian, Zimei.
鹤年 子美
Come.
来
Dad will wash the pigeon cage with you.
爸爸跟你们一块洗鸽子笼
Dad, you don't like Yingying, do you?
爸爸 你不是不喜欢英英吗
Who says I don't like Yingying?
谁说我不喜欢英英
The white cloud Yingying Baiyun, reveals its grass.
英英白云 露彼菅茅
Of course I like him.
我当然喜欢了
Sister, look, Yingying's eyes are so bright.
姐姐 你看英英的眼睛好亮
[Tianqiao New World Amusement Park]
[天桥新世界游艺场]
Shouchang and the others, where are they?
守常他们在哪儿
They have gone to Chengnan Amusement Park.
他们去城南游艺园了
It's agreed that after the leaflets are distributed,
说好了等撒完传单之后
everybody gathers in the Red Chamber Library.
大家到红楼图书馆集合
Didn't you say this is the busiest place in Beijing?
不是说这是北京最热闹的地方吗
I don't think there's many people.
我看也没多少人哪
[Gao Yihan, Professor at Peking University]
[高一涵 北京大学教授]
Wait a little longer.
再等一会儿
Don't worry, don't worry.
别着急 别着急
[Chengnan Amusement Park]
[城南游艺园]
Sir, this way.
先生这边
Come.
来
You take the seat.
您上座
Hurrah! Hurrah!
好好好
Hurrah!
好
Zhongxie.
仲澥
[Deng Zhongxia, styled Zhongxie, Student at Peking University]
[邓中夏 字 仲澥 北京大学学生]
Here's the plan.
这样
Guodao, you're in charge of keeping watch.
国焘 你负责把风
Shiyan, you're in charge.
世炎 你负责策应
Zhongxie, you'll be over there later.
仲澥 一会儿你在那儿撒
Okay.
好
I'm going to the second floor.
我去二楼
The second floor is too large, easy to be seen by below.
二楼目标太大了 容易被人盯死
I'd better go.
还是我去吧
It's okay. Leave it to me.
没事 交给我吧
Sir.
先生
If something happens later,
一会儿如果出现情况的话
you must withdraw to the west gate.
您一定要往西门撤
Let Master Ge and Xiaoshan
我让葛师傅和小山
coordinate with us over there.
在那边策应我们
What do you tell them about this little thing?
这点小事你通知他们干什么
Now you are the most wanted person in the police department.
您现在是警察厅最想抓的人
I'm afraid of danger
我怕出危险
Shiyan, you go to Master Ge and the others.
世炎 你去找葛师傅他们
Wait for my signal.
等我的信号 好
Let’s begin.
开始吧
Okay.
好
Almost there. Let's go.
人差不多了 开始吧
Okay, let's go down and scatter it.
好嘞 咱下去撒去
Where are you going?
去哪儿
Don't even think about it here.
你千万别想着在这儿撒
Spreading leaflets upstairs is the most dangerous thing.
在楼上撒传单是最危险的
Once we're blocked,
一旦被堵住的话
there is no place to retreat.
退的地方都没有
Look, there are so many people down there now.
你看现在下面人这么多
Let's mingle with the crowd.
咱们混在人群当中
It's so long to walk
一路走着一路撒
all the way.
路这么长
In case something else happens,
万一出点什么其他事
if you want to fall back, you can fall back in all directions.
要退的话 四面八方都好退
Okay.
好
You go down first, and I'll follow.
你先下去 我随后
Two people have a big goal together,
两个人在一起目标大
you go first,
你先去
separately.
分开撒
Ok, let's sprinkle it at the same time
行 那咱们同时撒
Okay.
好嘞
Raging from the sky, (from Peking opera《挑滑车》)
怒冲霄
even if his soldiers mountain down,
哪怕他兵山倒
and kill him in a bloody wilderness,
杀他个血染荒郊
I, single-handedly destroying the thieves,
单枪匹马把贼剿
will rid away the wolf smoke (=signal for war),
俺要把狼烟尽扫
As the horse rushes out of the battlefield,
一马冲出战场道
I will rid the thieves with dignity!
俺定要威风抖擞把贼扫
What's going on?
怎么回事
What?
什么东西
What is this?
这什么呀这
Fellow citizens,
同胞们
unite together!
团结起来
Resolutely resist the shameless Paris Peace Treaty!
坚决抵制无耻的巴黎和约
Fellow citizens,
同胞们
read at the "Beijing Citizen Manifesto"!
请看 《北京市民宣言》
Everyone should unite!
大家要团结起来
Resolutely resist the Paris Peace Treaty!
坚决抵制巴黎和约
Zhang Zongxiang, Cao Rulin
章宗祥 曹汝霖
must be expelled from Beijing!
驱逐出北京
Everyone should unite!
大家要团结起来
Resolutely resist the unequal Paris Peace Treaty!
坚决抵制不平等的巴黎和约
We must stick together!
一定要坚持到底
Unite together!
团结起来
"Beijing Citizen Manifesto"!
《北京市民宣言》
Resolutely refuse to sign the shameful Paris Peace Treaty!
坚决拒签可耻的巴黎和约
Resolutely expel the traitors Xu Shuzheng, Cao Rulin,
坚决把卖国贼徐树铮 曹汝霖
Lu Zongyu, Zhang Zongxiang,
陆宗舆 章宗祥
Duan Zhigui, Wang Huaiqing
段芝贵 王怀庆
from Beijing!
驱逐出北京
How daring to spread that!
还敢撒呀
He doesn't want to live anymore, does he?
这不要命了这是
Yeah.
是啊
Fellow citizens,
同胞们
here comes the police!
警察来了
Go quickly!
快走快走
Fellow citizens,
同胞们
the country needs you!
国家需要你们
Please look at the "Beijing Citizen Manifesto"!
请看《北京市民宣言》
Everyone should unite!
大家要团结起来
Grab the white one, that one!
抓住那个 白衣服那个
Don't run!
别跑
Fellow citizens,
同胞们
unite together!
团结起来
Second floor!
二楼
Fellow citizens,
同胞们
unite together!
团结起来
Sir, let's go!
先生 快走
Look, there's more.
快看快看 还有呢
What's this? It's
什么呀这是
the "Beijing Citizen Manifesto".
《北京市民宣言》
Get into action!
行动起来
Get out of the way! Get out of the way!
让开 让开 让开
Get out of the way!
让开让开
Don't let him get away!
别让他跑了
Chen Duxiu!
陈独秀
Go upstairs!
快 上楼
Go get him!
上 逮住他
Go upstairs! Go upstairs!
快 上楼上楼
Come down quickly!
你快下来
And him!
还有他
Grab him! Don't let him get away!
抓住他 别让他跑了
There is another one over there!
那边还有一个
Get him! Get him!
抓住他 抓住他
Stop!
站住 站住
Stay close to him!
跟紧他
Get into action!
行动起来
Chen Duxiu?
陈独秀吗
Get down!
下来
Hurry up and get down!
赶紧给我下来
Students,
学生
merchants,
商人
labourers,
劳工
soldiers!
军人
Resolutely resist the humiliating Paris Peace Treaty!
坚决抵制屈辱的巴黎和约
Shut up! Shut up!
给我住嘴 闭嘴
Shut up!
给我闭嘴
Take him away!
带走
Move! Move!
走 走
Keep moving!
快走
Move!
走吧
Done.
好了
Rub some oil.
来 擦点油
Mom!
妈妈
Mom will wipe it on you right away.
妈妈马上给你抹啊
Come.
来
What's going on?
什么情况
I have searched the first, second, third colleges and the Red Building.
一院二院三院还有红楼都找了
No one.
没人
So Liu Mei, Bai Lan,
这样 柳眉白兰
you guys stay.
你们留下来
Take care of two little ones sleeping at home.
在家照顾两个小的睡觉
Don't go out!
千万不许出去啊
Yannian, you go to Mr. Shouchang's house
延年 你去守常先生家
Qiaonian and I will go to Mr. Shizhi's house.
乔年 跟我去适之先生家
Okay.
好
Let's keep looking for him.
咱们接着找 走
Chen Duxiu has been arrested for disturbing public order.
陈独秀扰乱社会治安 已被拘捕
We were ordered to search.
我们奉命搜查
Search!
给我搜
Everybody in the back, come here!
后边的人 都给我过来
You! What's your name?
你 叫什么
Chen Yannian.
陈延年
What about you?
你呢
Chen Qiaonian.
陈乔年
You!
你
Bai Lan.
白兰
What are you doing?
干什么你
I'm telling you,
我告诉你
now you're just ordered to search.
你现在只是奉命搜查
If you dare to hurt my family,
你要是敢伤害我的家人
dare to touch a child's finger,
敢动孩子一根手指头
I'll fight you with my life.
我拿命跟你拼
Check them carefully for me.
仔细给我查
Don't move.
过去
Nobody move.
都别动
Get back.
回去
Shouchang.
守常
Something's wrong. Something's wrong.
出事了 出大事了
Brother Zhongfu.
仲甫兄呢
Zhongfu was caught by the police.
仲甫被警察抓住了
The scene was a mess.
现场是一片混乱
I also took advantage of the chaos to get out.
我也是趁乱才跑出来的
Where has Zhongfu been caught?
仲甫被抓到哪儿去了
Unclear.
不清楚
Zhongfu shouted loudly when he was caught by the police.
仲甫被警察抓住的时候高声呼叫
I--
我
I didn't dare to stay there and ask more questions.
我就没敢留在那儿多打听
Sir.
先生
I--
我
I can't stay here any longer.
这儿不能多待了
The police will be here soon.
警察很快就会到
Go out and hide.
您赶紧出去躲一躲
Don't panic, don't mess around.
别慌 别乱
Make it clear what's going on.
说清楚了 到底怎么回事
My father has been detained.
我父亲已经被拘留了
The police just searched my house.
警察刚去我家搜查过
Please leave Beijing quickly.
您赶快离开北京
It's too dangerous here.
这儿太危险了
I'll save him.
我去救他
Sir, you can't go.
先生 您不能去
Shouchang, you can't go.
守常 你不能去
You dare not show your face outside again.
你不敢再在外面露面了
Didn't you listen to Yannian?
你没听延年说吗
The police are looking everywhere to arrest you.
警察正到处抓你呢
You have to run quickly.
你得赶快跑
Run?
跑
Where am I going?
我往哪儿跑
I want to get him out.
我要把他救出来
Mr. Shouchang.
守常先生
You're not listening to me now.
您现在不 听我说
Zhongfu is a celebrity.
仲甫属于社会名流
The police should not dare to do anything to him.
警察应该也不敢把他怎么样
He will naturally be rescued.
他也自然会有人救
But your situation is different from Zhongfu's.
但你的情况跟仲甫的情况不一样
You have to get out and hide.
你得赶快出去躲一躲
Yihan, let me tell you.
一涵 我告诉你
If I'm not saving brother Zhongfu,
不把仲甫兄救出来
I'm not going anywhere.
我哪儿都不会去
Sir, what are you---
先生 你这是
What are you holding me for?
你们拉着我干什么
Shouchang, why are you so confused?
守常 你怎么这么糊涂呢
Just go back to your hometown in Hebei for a while.
你就先回河北老家去避一避嘛
When will the situation here come down,
等什么时候这边情况一松下来
we'll pick you up again.
我们再去把你接回来
Sir.
先生
Liu Yipin has come here with the police.
刘一品带着警察已经往这儿来了
He sid to check Dean Chen's office
说是要检查陈学长的办公室
and the libraries.
和图书馆
Mr. Shouchang, you have to go quickly.
守常先生 你得赶紧走了
Don't panic, everyone. Calm down.
大家先别慌 镇静一下
Let's split the work.
咱们分一下工
Haiwei, Master Ge,
海威 葛师傅
Xiaoshan,
小山
you three escort Mr. Shouchang out of town.
你们三个护送守常先生出城
Yannian, Shiyan,
延年世炎
you go to Mr. Hu Shi
你们去找胡适先生
and tell him to inform the news media
让他通报各个新闻媒介
to try every means to rescue Mr. Zhongfu.
想尽办法营救仲甫先生
Mr. Yihan, please.
一涵先生 麻烦您
Please.
拜托您
Write down the arrest of Mr. Zhongfu
把仲甫先生被捕的经过
in detail.
详细写一下
We should inform the Federation of Students.
我们要通报学联
Sir, there is no time.
先生 没有时间了
Let's go.
赶紧走吧
I'm not leaving.
我不会走的
I won't.
我不会
Hurry!
赶紧走
Sir, let's go!
先生 先走
Go.
走
Okay.
好
Are you kidding?
开什么玩笑啊
A celebrity!
社会名流
The leader of New Culture!
新文化的领袖
Will he only talk in shackles and handcuffs?
能戴着脚镣手拷说话吗
You're afraid he'll fly?
你怕他飞了
Don't open it for him yet.
还不给他打开
Yes.
是
Key.
钥匙
Go, go, go, take away.
掌走掌走拿走
You all go down.
你们都下去吧
Yes.
是
We meet again, old friend.
老乡 咱们又见面了
Chief Wu.
吴总监
Looks like you arranged this meeting.
看来你安排这次见面
It took a lot of effort.
费了不少心机啊
Exactly.
那是
To invite someone as important as you here,
能把你这么重要的人物请到这儿来
I tried my best to move mountains.
我可是费尽了移山之力呀
Why should you arrest me?
凭什么抓我呀
You see.
看看
I, Wu Bingxiang,
我吴炳湘
will never do anything you are not sure about.
从来不做没有把握的事情
Let me read it to you.
我来给你念念啊
Chen Duxiu, a professor at Peking University,
查北京大学教授陈独秀
was detained and examined for inciting the public
以私印并传播印刷品
against the government
传播过激主义
by privately printing and distributing printed materials
煽动民众对抗政府 扰乱治安
and spreading radicalism.
予以拘留审查
I am a citizen of the Republic of China.
我是中华民国的公民
I love my country.
我爱我的国家
Distributing leaflets in public
当众散发传单
to to refuse to sign the Paris Peace Treaty
要求拒签巴黎和约
and severely punish the traitors,
严惩卖国贼
what's the crime of this patriotic act?
这是爱国行为 何罪之有啊
Professor Chen,
陈教授
I want to remind you that
我想提醒你的是
this isn't your Peking University,
这儿不是你们北京大学
a forum for academic discussion.
进行学术辩论的讲坛
Are you guilty?
你有没有罪
You say no.
你说了不算
The law has the final say.
法律说了算
Now that you are here,
既然你已经到了这儿
you have to be judged by the law.
就得接受法律的审判
But I also want to tell you,
不过我还想告诉你哪
you'd better make this mental preparation.
你最好做好这个精神上的准备
I'm afraid you'll have to stay here a few more days.
恐怕你要在这儿多待些日子了
I'll stay here, no problem.
我待在这儿没问题
What worries me is
我担心的是
how will you, Chief Wu, end up in the future?
你吴总监将来怎么收场
You're right.
你说得没错
The news that you, Chen Duxiu, were arrested
今天你陈独秀被捕的消息
broke today,
一经传出
must be the headlines of major newspapers
那必然成为各大报纸的新闻头条
in this city and even all of China.
这北京城乃至中国
What will it be like?
会闹腾成什么样子
It's hard to say.
这都很难说呀
Maybe I, Wu Bingxiang, will become
也许我吴炳湘会成为
like Cao, Zhang, and Lu,
继曹 章 陆之后的
the fourth traitor who will be criticized.
第四个被口诛笔伐的卖国贼
But let me tell you something,
不过我告诉你
since I can invite you here,
我既然能把你请到这儿来
I made all the preparations.
我就做好了一切准备
I will never give up halfway.
我绝对不会半途而废
Very good, very determined.
很好决心很大
Courageous.
勇气可嘉
Professor Chen, let me tell you something,
陈教授 我告诉你啊
we are both fellow villagers.
念咱们两是老乡啊
I should take care of you.
我对你应该有所照顾
Say, what terms do you want to make here?
说吧 在这儿你想提出什么条件
Just say it.
你只管开口
Then I'll be blunt.
那我不客气 直说了
Go ahead, please.
你说吧
I hope I have the right to read and write.
我希望有看书和写作的权利
Of course you can.
那当然可以啊
Solitary confinement.
单独监禁嘛
But what you write can't get out.
但是 所写的东西不能传出去
That.
那
No can do.
不发不发
As long as I can read and write,
我只要能看书写作就行
for me,
对我来说
a prison and a laboratory are the same thing.
监狱和研究室是一回事
Professor Chen, let me tell you something.
陈教授 我告诉你啊
You wouldn't be Professor Chen here.
你在这儿就不是陈教授了
Who am I then?
那我是谁
You are a very important suspect in the police department.
你是警察厅一名非常重要的嫌犯
They want to give you a number
他们要给你个编号
to replace your name.
取代你的名字
Number?
编号
What number is he?
他多少号
No. 178.
一七八号
178.
一七八
I hope you can behave yourself.
希望你能好自为之
I will often come to see you.
我会常来看你
Messenger.
来人
Here.
到
Take the No. 178 to his new house.
带一七八号去他的新居
Yes.
是
Okay.
好
Come on.
来吧
Please.
请吧
Go by yourself.
自己走啊
Fellow teachers!
各位老师
Fellow students!
各位同学
Just yesterday,
就在昨天
Mr. Sun Yat-sen in Shanghai
远在上海的孙中山先生
met Xu Shichang
会见了徐世昌
and Duan Qirui's representatives in the peace talks.
段祺瑞的和谈代表
He solemnly proposed to them at the meeting
他在会议上郑重地向他们提出
about the arrest of Mr. Chen Duxiu.
关于陈独秀先生被捕的事情
Mr. Sun Yat-sen said this.
孙中山先生是这样说的
My companions and I were very shocked.
我和我的同伴们都十分地震惊
Your thousand good deeds
你们千的好事
are enough to convince all citizens.
足以使所有国民都相信
I am right to oppose you.
我反对你们是没错
But I don't think you dare kill him.
不过我看 你们也不敢把他杀死
For killing a man,
因为杀死了一个人
means killing fifty,
就会出现五十个
one hundred.
一百个
So just do it.
所以你们尽管干吧
Classmates.
同学们
I call everyone to unite again.
我再次呼大家团结起来
Protest against the government's unwarranted arrests.
抗议政府无故抓人
Release Mr. Chen Duxiu immediately!
立即释放陈独秀先生
[Hanwen Temple, Wufengshan, Changli, Hebei]
[河北昌黎五峰山韩文公祠]
Student Zhongxie.
仲澥同学
Recently, Beijing students
近日北京学生
and people from all walks of life are rescuing Zhongfu very well.
及各界营救仲甫行动甚好
Only the rescue activities should be combined with the refusal to sign the Paris Peace Treaty
唯应将营救活动与拒签巴黎和约
to severely punish traitors, etc.
挽蔡行动严惩卖国贼等
It is more effective to combine closely.
紧密结合起来才更有效
Zhongfu flew close to the fire,
仲甫飞蛾扑火
intending to promote the May Fourth Movement.
意在促进五四运动
to a deeper level.
向更深层次发展
Don't disappoint his painstaking efforts.
切莫辜负了他的一片苦心啊
You should understand,
你们应该明了
to force the reactionary government to refuse to sign the Paris Peace Treaty
实现逼迫反动政府拒签巴黎和约
is the latest goal of this movement.
是这一运动最近的目标
Shizhi asked us to come.
这个 适之叫我们来
What are you doing?
是干什么呀
He probably has something to do with magazines.
他这个八成还是杂志方面的事
[Lu Xun, Civil servant under the Ministry of Education]
[鲁迅 教育部佥事]
Now Mr. Cai has left without return.
如今蔡先生出走未归
Hu Renyuan, the new principal, is afraid to take office.
新任校长胡仁源又不敢到职
Zhongfu was arrested and Shouchang took refuge.
仲甫被捕 守常避难
Peking University is at the center of the political vortex.
北大正处于政治旋涡的中心
It's really a bad fate.
真可谓命运多舛
In this troubled time,
既逢多事之秋
We need to actively think
我们也看实需要
of countermeasures.
积极地想想对策才是啊
Gentlemen.
诸位
Shizhi.
适之
Sorry for being late.
抱歉 来晚了
I was just now in the classroom
刚才在教室里面
answering questions for students.
给学生解答问题来着
[Hu Shi, styled Shizhi, Professor at Peking University]
[胡适 字 适之 北京大学教授]
Everyone is called today.
今天叫大家过来
The purpose may be clear in everyone's mind.
目的可能大家心里都清楚了
Zhongfu is in jail and Shouchang has left Beijing.
仲甫入狱 守常出京
Now our "New Youth"
现在咱们的 《新青年》
and the "Weekly Review"
和《每周评论》
are in a state of suspension of publication.
都处在一个停刊的状态
What should we do next?
接下来应该怎么办
I made my own decisions.
我自作主张
I invite my colleagues to make a decision.
把各位同人请来做个决断
Shizhi, the top priority is to rescue Zhongfu.
适之 当务之急是营救仲甫啊
He founded and is responsible for both publications.
两个刊物都是他创办和负责的
It's hard for others to take over without him.
他不在 别人很难接手
Uhh--
这
Actually, I invited everyone here.
其实 我把大家请过来
I have an idea.
我有个想法
I thought twice about this idea.
这个想法是我考虑再三的
I feel that at this time of crisis,
我觉得现在值此危难之时
I should be brave enough to take more responsibility.
我应该急流勇进 多些担当
So I want to volunteer
所以我想主动请缨
to undertake the editing of two magazines.
来承担两本杂志的编辑工作
I don't know what you think.
不知诸位意下如何
[Qian Xuantong, styled Deqian, Professor at Peking University]
[钱玄同 字 德潜 北京大学教授]
I don't trust you, Shizhi.
不是不信任你 适之
Brother Zhongfu brought "New Youth".
《新青年》仲甫兄带来的
He's not here. I thought
他不在 我以为
none of us can replace him.
我们之中没有人可以替代他
It's better to stop first.
莫不如先停下来
Let's talk about it after brother Zhongfu gets out of prison.
等仲甫兄出狱之后再说
As for the "Weekly Review",
至于《每周评论》
at the moment
当前看
it seems to have a great effect on rescuing Zhongfu.
似乎对营救仲甫的作用很大
It should be continued.
应该继续办下去
I agree with Mr. Lu Xun.
我同意鲁迅先生的意思
The "Weekly Review" must continue.
《每周评论》必须继续办下去
I agree with Lu Xun.
我同意鲁迅的意见
"New Youth" is suspended.
《新青年》 暂停
The "Weekly Review" can be taken over by Shizhi.
《每周评论》可由适之接手
I will try my best.
诸位 我一定努力
In addition, Mr. Shouchang also suggested that
此外 守常先生还提出
we should take advantage of the situation
我们应该因势利导
to establish the All-China Students’ Federation as soon as possible.
尽快成立全国学联
In schools all over the country,
在全国各校都在广泛地
a widespread campaign to rescue Chen Duxiu is being launched,
发起营救陈独秀运动
using this fuse
利用这个导火索
to integrate the national student forces together
把全国学生力量整合在一起
into a unified leading body.
成立统一的领导机构
This is an excellent opportunity.
这 是一个绝好的机会
I propose to set up the All-China Federation of Students in Shanghai.
我提议把全国学联设在上海
Because now it looks like
因为现在看起来
Shanghai has become the center of the national movement.
上海已经成为全国运动的中心了
Li Dazhao.
李大钊
Hurrah!
好 好
There is hope.
有希望了
Students.
同学们
Today's "Weekly Review"
今天《每周评论》上
published a short poem
发表了一篇短诗
"Embrace Chen Duxiu".
《怀陈独秀》
[Zhao Shiyan, styled Qinsheng, Student at The High School Affiliated to Beijing Normal University]
[赵世炎 字 琴生 北京高等师范附中学生]
There was a strong response among the students.
在学生中反响强烈
How about I read it to you?
我给大家朗诵一遍怎么样
Yes!
好
According to their claim,
依他们的主张
our common people are suffering.
我们小百姓痛苦
According to your opinion,
依你的主张
they are in pain.
他们痛苦
They don't want pain,
他们不愿意痛苦
so you're in pain.
所以你痛苦
Your pain
你痛苦
is to suffer for us.
是替我们痛苦
Petition representatives from various provinces in Beijing
各省来京请愿代表
will then petition the Presidential Palace
随后将往总统府请愿
It's been a long journey for you.
一路上舟车劳顿 辛苦你们了
Nothing. I'm used to walking on mountain roads.
没事 山路都走惯了
Yannian is just ahead.
延年就在前面
Yannian!
延年
Come, come, let me introduce
来来来 我介绍一下
the President of the Shaanxi Students Federation.
这位是陕西学生联合会的会长
This is Chen Yannian.
这位便是陈延年同学
[Qu Wu]
[屈武]
Hello, hello, hello.
你好你好你好
We Shaanxi students
我们陕西学子
admire Mr. Chen Duxiu very much.
十分地敬仰陈独秀先生
So I was asked to bring this pennant
所以特意托我带了这面锦旗
to pay tribute.
聊表敬意
Please also forward it for you.
还请您代为转交
Thank you very much.
感谢
I'm sorry for my father.
我替家父愧领了
Students.
同学们
The day of signing the Paris Peace Treaty is coming
巴黎和约签字的日子就要到了
and the Beiyang government had already sent telegrams to all provinces.
北洋政府已经通电各省
Lu Zhengxiang in Paris
并专电巴黎陆征祥
said that if the protest is ineffective,
表示如果抗议无效
they will just sign the peace treaty.
就在和约上签字
From today, Beijing and Paris will join forces
今天起 北京巴黎两地联合行动
with petition representatives from various provinces in Beijing
各省来京请愿代表
to petition the Presidential Palace
随后将到总统府请愿
and will never retreat until they see Xu Shichang.
不见到徐世昌决不收兵
There will be 30,000 Chinese in Paris
巴黎将有三万华人
surrounding the Chinese envoy's residence
包围中国专使驻地
and Lu Zhengxiang's residence
以及陆征祥官邸
to resolutely prevent the Chinese representatives from signing.
坚决阻止中国代表签字
Our Beijing Federation of Students
我们北京学联
will actively cooperate with provincial petition representatives.
将积极配合各省请愿代表
and provide support.
并做好后援
Students' success or failure is at stake.
同学们 成败在此一举
We will not stop until we achieve our goal!
不达目的 决不罢休
Brother Juren.
菊人兄
[Qian Nengxun, styled Xicheng, Premier of the Beiyang Government]
[钱能训 字 傒丞 北洋政府国务总理]
Forgive me. I really can't be with you.
原谅我实在不能奉陪了
[Xu Shichang, pen name Juren, President of the Republic of China]
[徐世昌 号 菊人 中华民国总统]
I--
我
Look at your little promise.
你看你那点出息
A Chen Duxiu scared you like this?
一个陈独秀就把你吓成这样了
I--
我
Sit.
坐
Brother Ju Ren.
菊人兄
Then Chen Duxiu, Li Dazhao,
那陈独秀李大钊
and the student movement they lead.
和他们领导的学生运动
It's a disaster.
简直是洪水猛兽
They represent a trend.
他们代表了一股潮流
You can't stop it at all.
你我根本阻挡不了啊
This world is really going to change.
这世道吧 真是要大变喽
You said that, in China for thousands of years,
你说 中国几千年了
what scared the ruler
能让统治者害怕的
was the changing dynasties.
能够改朝换代的
That is, the peasants uprising.
也就是农民起义了吧
But now the peasants have not rebelled.
可现在好了 农民没起义
The-
可
The scholars rebelled.
秀才造反了
It's turned upside down
搅得天翻地覆的
and yields to nothing.
而且 软硬不吃
He's got no temper.
拿他没脾气
Peasants uprising is not terrible.
农民起义不可怕
Peasants uprising do not change the course.
农民起义改朝不改道啊
But now these people,
但现在这帮人
they're not only going to change the dynasty,
他们不光要改朝
but change the course, change the system,
还要改道 改制
change the thinking.
改脑袋
What do you mean?
什么意思
Ideology. Theories.
思想 理论
They want to transform China with foreign theories.
他们要用外国的理论来改造中国
Theory?
理论
What theory? This is what you say.
什么理论这是 你说说
I don't know.
我也说不清楚
All I know is that I am behind the times.
我只知道 我已经落伍了
It's still possible to retire from politics to protect a little face
急流勇退尚可保一丝颜面
and still make it to the end,
死扛到底
but it will be condemned in history for thousands of years.
只能遗臭万年
Brother Juren.
菊人兄
Just give me a break.
你就饶了我吧
Okay, okay, okay.
好 好 好
Go then.
走吧
Retire from politics.
急流勇退
Save your face.
保你的脸面去吧
Go then.
走吧
I can't walk anymore.
我已走不了了
I can only be remembered.
我只能遗臭万年了
27 June 1919,
一九一九年六月二十七日
hundreds of representatives from petition groups in Beijing.
北京及各地请愿团代表数百人
petitioned to the Presidential Palace
赴总统府请愿
asking the Beiyang government to refuse to sign the peace treaty.
要求北洋政府拒绝在和约上签字
After two days and one night of struggle,
经过两天一夜的斗争
on the night of the 28th,
二十八日晚
Xu Shichang was forced to meet with ten delegates.
徐世昌被迫接见了十名代表
Among them, Shaanxi representative Qu Wu
其中 陕西代表屈武
resisted to death by banging his head on the ground out of patriotic indignation.
基于爱国的义愤 以头撞地以死抗争
History records "Blood was spattered in the Presidential Palace"
史称 "血溅总统府"
Xu Shichang was forced to agree to the students' demands.
徐世昌被迫答应学生的要求
Ah, let's eat and work
咱们啊 边吃边干活
[Nankai School, Tianjin]
[天津南开学校]
Do you mind eating halal today?
今天吃清真大家没意见吧
We don't mind!
没意见
Students.
同学们
Our Beijing-Tianjin joint petition campaign
我们京津联合发起的
to save Cai and save Chen
挽蔡救陈请愿活动
can be said to be a great success.
可以说是大获成功啊
Everyone is united with one heart and one mind,
大家同心同德 团结一致
not afraid of bloodshed and sacrifice,
不怕流血牺牲
especially our president, Ma Jun.
特别是我们的会长 马骏同学
For our Tianjin academic circles
为我们天津学界
he is the glory of fame.
是争了光 扬了名
Don't we have to congratulate?
咱们是不是得祝贺一下啊
Clap everyone!
鼓掌
You said so.
你这么说的呀
I'm sorry.
我都不好意思
Ma is really powerful.
老马 真厉害啊
That loud voice shouted in front of Tiananmen.
天安门前大嗓门那一喊
[Deng Yingchao]
[邓颖超]
It's really worthy of your big beard.
真是配得上你这一脸大胡子
A roar in front of Yangqiao.
当阳桥前一声吼
I see,
我看
don't call yourself Ma Jun from now on.
你以后就别叫马骏了
Change your name to Ma Tianan.
你改名叫马天安得了
That's a good name.
这个名字不错
That's a good idea.
这个主意好
Everybody, journalists!
大家记着啊
Starting from today,
从今天开始
my name is Ma Tianan.
我就叫马天安了
This name is loud and clear.
这个名字 响亮
Memorable!
有纪念意义
Ma Tianan,
马天安
don't be too proud.
你别太得意了啊
I want to give you a piece of advice.
我要给你提个意见
There are five or six hundred people from our Tianjin Federation of Students this time,
这次我们天津学联来了有五六百人
[Liu Qingyang]
[刘清扬]
but there is no unified command.
可是却没有一个统一的指挥部
Patriotic comrades in the academic and female circles
学联和女界的爱国同志
will go their own way and distract the power.
会各行其是 分散了力量
As a result, many students left the team.
结果就有不少同学掉了队
I think it's a great lesson.
我认为啊 这是一个很大的教训
Exactly.
没错
Our female classmates were notified late.
我们女同学得到通知晚了
[Zhou Enlai, styled Xiangyu, editor-in-chief of the "Tianjin Student Union Newspaper"]
[周恩来 字 翔宇 《天津学生联合会报》主编]
They almost blocked it back.
差点让他们给堵了回去
It's my fault.
这事怪我
I was late in notifying.
是我通知晚了
It's not your personal business either.
这也不是你个人的事情
It's an organizational problem.
是组织机构上的问题
I have a proposal.
我有个提议
Please merge your Tianjin Federation of Students with us
你们天津学联和我们合并吧
to form a unified leading body,
组成一个统一的领导机构
and it can also be able to assume
而且还能负担起
leadership of the Tianjin patriotic youth movement?
天津爱国青年运动的领导责任呢
What do you think?
你们觉得呢
This suggestion is good.
这个建议好
I agree.
我同意
I also agree.
我也同意
I think
我认为
it is not necessary to merge the two organizations.
不一定非要把两个组织合并起来
The most important
最重要的
is to build a core team that can become the backbone
是建立起一个能够成为天津学界
of the Tianjin academic community.
主心骨的核心团队
So
所以
I suggest that the backbone of the Federation of Students and the Women's Comradeship Association
我建议把学联和女界同志会的骨干
be organized
组织起来
into a more organized patriotic group
成立一个组织更为严密的爱国团体
that not only leads the student movement
不光领导学生运动
but also conducts scientific and new ideological research.
还要进行科学和新思潮的研究
and publishes a journal
同时出版一种刊物
to guide the student movement
指导学生运动
to become the leading core of the Tianjin academic community.
成为天津学界的领导核心
I think
我觉得啊
brother Enlai's proposal is very good.
恩来兄这个提议非常好
What about me?
我呢
Raise your hands in agreement.
举双手赞同
Thank you.
谢谢
And sign up.
并且报名参加
I also think Enlai's opinion stands higher.
我也觉得恩来的这个意见站位更高
I agree.
我同意
I agree. I agree, too.
我也同意 我也同意
Then Enlai,
那恩来
let's leave the preparatory work of this organization
这个组织的筹备工作
to you.
就由你来负责吧
No problem.
没问题
Your Women's Patriotic Comradeship Association
你们女界爱国同志会
should send someone to assist him.
派一个人协助他
Then, Wenshu, come.
那文淑 你来吧
Good.
好
Let's think of a name for this organization.
那我们给这个组织想个名字吧
I guess
我想
our organization will be called
我们这个组织就叫
the Awakening Society.
觉悟社吧
Awakening Society?
觉悟社
Yes, the Awakening Society.
对 觉悟社
We will go to Beijing in a few days
过几天我们去一趟北京
and ask Mr. Li Dazhao to give us some advice.
找李大钊先生再帮我们出出主意
That's a good idea.
这是个好主意
Let's eat!
吃饭
Alright!
来 好
[Hôtel Lutetia, Paris]
[巴黎 吕特蒂旅馆]
[Gu Weiju, styled Shaochuan, Ambassador to the United States]
[顾维钧 字 少川 驻美公使]
[Wang Zhengting, styled Rutang, Plenipotentiary of the Southern Government]
[王正廷 字 儒堂 南方政府特命全权大使]
I read in the newspaper that
我看报纸说
that the French are all impressed
这几天法国人对中国人
by the Chinese these days.
全都刮目相看了
They think
他们认为
Chinese people are surprisingly bloodthirsty.
中国人竟然如此有血性
The sleeping lion was finally awakened.
这头睡狮终于被唤醒了
It's not easy.
不容易啊
I heard that the Chinese have organized death squads.
我听说华人已经组织了敢死队
Three people for a minister's life.
用三个人换一条公使的命
Thousands of people have signed up.
报名者 竟达千人之多
Qingdao is ours!
青岛是我们的
Shandong is ours!
山东是我们的
I really want to go down
我真想下去
and tell them what I think.
跟他们说说我的想法